Mohawk River Mills Records 6790
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Mohawk River Mills Records
1850-1885
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Mohawk River Mills
6790
0.75 cubic feet
0.8 linear ft.
.
10747770
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
M. Farwell, March 21, 2019
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 21, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The company, located in Cohoes, N.Y., was founded in 1854 to manufacture "woven goods of various kinds." It carried inventories of both cotton and wool machinery. The Cohoes Co., organized in 1826, was formed to build a dam and power canal system on the Mohawk River at Cohoes. Most textile mills in the area purchased water-power and rented land from the Cohoes Co.
Scope and Contents
Mohawk River Mills, Cohoes, NY. Business records, 1854-1885 (ca. 250 items). Includes certificate of incorporation, contract to construct a factory, minutes of meetings of stockholders & trustees, and correspondence of Truman G. Younglove, company president. Also accounts with Cohoes Iron Foundry and Machine Shop; water rent accounts for Mohawk and for Flax Cotton Mills building; bills and receipts, production and payroll records; inventories of stock on hand, including those for Watervliet Mills, Halcyon Mills and Atlantic Mills; and sales records and financial statements. Also a few records of Flax Cotton Mills and Harmony Mills.
Custodial History
American Textile History Museum Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Business records; Cotton manufacture; Financial records; Flax Cotton Mills.; Industries; Textile industry; Wages; Water-power; Woolen and worsted manufacture; Mohawk River (N.Y.); Bailey, Joshua.; Younglove, Truman G.; Atlantic Mills (Lawrence, Mass.); Cohoes Company.; Cohoes Iron Foundry and Machine Shop.; Halcyon Mills.; Harmony Mills (Cohoes, N.Y.); Mohawk River Mills.; Watervliet Mills.
10747770
- Certificate of Incorporation (copy), 1854 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  1854-02-13
- Contract for Joshua Bailey (draft), 1854 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Proposition to Mr. Bailey (Box 1, Folder 3)
  For land and water power for mill with sketch and notes. 4 items. Undated
- Stock installment receipts, 1854-1855 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Share subscriptions, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letter to J. Knower, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Demanding payment for shares
- Stockholders and Trustees minutes, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Stockholders and Trustees minutes, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Stockholders and Trustees minutes, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Stockholders and Trustees minutes, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Stockholders and Trustees minutes, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Stockholders and Trustees minutes, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Stockholders and Trustees minutes, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Cohes Iron Foundry and Machine Shop, 1850-1860 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Mill accounts
- Cohes Iron Foundry and Machine Shop, 1854-1861 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Water rent accounts (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Undated
- Receipts for water rent, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Account of labor from payroll, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  For carding and spinning rooms
- Cost of labor and stock, 1850-1859 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Approximately 1850-1859
- Bills and receipts, 1857-1885 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Statement of production, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Estimates of expenses and income, 1860-1861 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Many fragments. Approximately 1860-1861
- E. Atkinson's estimates for machinery for cotton yarns, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Inventories at the mill and in Boston, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Inventory of Watervoleit Mills, Halcyon Mills, and Atlantic Mills, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Sketches of sales, memos, and notes, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Account of John R. Bullock, 1857-1858 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- J.G. Root and Co. Smith Gregory and Co., B.A. Sweet accounts, 1858-1859 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Stephen Slocum account, 1857-1861 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Hugh Thompson account, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Mohawk River Mill balances, 1854-1858 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Balance sheet of assets and notes, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Fragments. 1861 and undated
- Ledger balance, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Letters of patent transfer, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Disposition of fire insurance, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  1853-11-07
- List of materials required for Flax Cotton Mill, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  After November 1853
- Lease for Mohawk River Mill to Charles P. Barbar, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  1855-06-01
- Lease of Mohawk River Mill to Henry Brockway, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  1859-05-01
- Lease for Harmony Mills with Patrick Rogers, 1850-1859 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  Patrick Rogers of West Troy, New York. Approximately 1850-1859
- Correspondence - T.G. Younglove, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence - T.G. Younglove, 1856 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence - T.G. Younglove, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence - T.G. Younglove, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence - T.G. Younglove, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence - T.G. Younglove, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence - T.G. Younglove, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence - T.G. Younglove, 1866-1868 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence - Samuel Payson, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 9)